Historic New England
Bowen family papers
- Papers relating to the construction of Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1845-1969, undated, predominant 1845-1851; MS006.02; Business records (3 file boxes, 1 oversize folder); Series II, Papers relating to the construction of Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1845-1969, undated (
  - Work accounts re: laborers, September 1845 - November 1851; includes Lewis Chamberlin's work account, 1845-1851; MS006.02.03.01; Bowen family papers (MS006) Series II, Papers relating to the construction of Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1845-1969, undated (bulk: 1845-1851) (#6.25-6.27, 8.1-8.17, OB.1.4-OB.1.5), contains agreements and contracts (includes drafts); bills and receipts; building and construction specifications; correspondence; design and floor plans; drafts of checks; work account records; photographs; clippings; and a collection of papers describing the rooms at Roseland Cottage. The series is divided into three sections: contracts and specifications, financial records, and other materials. Contracts and specifications includes two drafts and a signed agreement between Henry Chandler Bowen and contractor, Samuel Underwood, regarding the furnishing of materials for construction of Roseland Cottage and an adjoining barn; specifications of architect, John C. Wells, for the carpentry and masonry work at Roseland Cottage and for the construction of the barn; and design and floor plans for the addition to the barn. The correspondence contains letters received by Henry Chandler Bowen relating to the construction work on Roseland Cottage. Several of the letters are from contractor, Samuel Underwood, requesting to be released from his contract; and other letters are from contractor, Edwin Eaton, detailing the work progress on the construction of Roseland Cottage and his decision to hire a Mr. Taylor of Brooklyn, New York, to complete the masonry work and a Mr. Joy of Worcester, Massachusetts, as foreman. The financial records include bills and receipts; drafts of checks; and work account records regarding the payment of laborers and the purchase of supplies associated with the construction of Roseland Cottage; the records were kept by Henry Chandler Bowen, Lewis Chamberlin, and Edwin Eaton. A collection of papers referred to as "Reminiscences of Roseland Cottage," describing the interior furnishings and rooms at Roseland Cottage, as recalled by Anna Mellon; photographs of a collection of paintin gs at Roseland Cottage (includes several photographs of Benjamin Franklin); and newspaper clippings relating to Roseland Cottage and its inhabitants, comprise the section of other materials. The series is arranged alphabetically by section, and thereunder chronologically. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Bills and receipts re: supplies, October-November 1846, MS006.02.03.02; Bowen family papers (MS006) Series II, Papers relating to the construction of Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1845-1969, undated (bulk: 1845-1851) (#6.25-6.27, 8.1-8.17, OB.1.4-OB.1.5), contains agreements and contracts (includes drafts); bills and receipts; building and construction specifications; correspondence; design and floor plans; drafts of checks; work account records; photographs; clippings; and a collection of papers describing the rooms at Roseland Cottage. The series is divided into three sections: contracts and specifications, financial records, and other materials. Contracts and specifications includes two drafts and a signed agreement between Henry Chandler Bowen and contractor, Samuel Underwood, regarding the furnishing of materials for construction of Roseland Cottage and an adjoining barn; specifications of architect, John C. Wells, for the carpentry and masonry work at Roseland Cottage and for the construction of the barn; and design and floor plans for the addition to the barn. The correspondence contains letters received by Henry Chandler Bowen relating to the construction work on Roseland Cottage. Several of the letters are from contractor, Samuel Underwood, requesting to be released from his contract; and other letters are from contractor, Edwin Eaton, detailing the work progress on the construction of Roseland Cottage and his decision to hire a Mr. Taylor of Brooklyn, New York, to complete the masonry work and a Mr. Joy of Worcester, Massachusetts, as foreman. The financial records include bills and receipts; drafts of checks; and work account records regarding the payment of laborers and the purchase of supplies associated with the construction of Roseland Cottage; the records were kept by Henry Chandler Bowen, Lewis Chamberlin, and Edwin Eaton. A collection of papers referred to as "Reminiscences of Roseland Cottage," describing the interior furnishings and rooms at Roseland Cottage, as recalled by Anna Mellon; photographs of a collection of paintin gs at Roseland Cottage (includes several photographs of Benjamin Franklin); and newspaper clippings relating to Roseland Cottage and its inhabitants, comprise the section of other materials. The series is arranged alphabetically by section, and thereunder chronologically. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Bills and receipts re: Joseph C. Wells, architect, November 20, 1846 and July 12, 1850, 1846-1850; MS006.02.03.03; Bowen family papers (MS006) Series II, Papers relating to the construction of Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1845-1969, undated (bulk: 1845-1851) (#6.25-6.27, 8.1-8.17, OB.1.4-OB.1.5), contains agreements and contracts (includes drafts); bills and receipts; building and construction specifications; correspondence; design and floor plans; drafts of checks; work account records; photographs; clippings; and a collection of papers describing the rooms at Roseland Cottage. The series is divided into three sections: contracts and specifications, financial records, and other materials. Contracts and specifications includes two drafts and a signed agreement between Henry Chandler Bowen and contractor, Samuel Underwood, regarding the furnishing of materials for construction of Roseland Cottage and an adjoining barn; specifications of architect, John C. Wells, for the carpentry and masonry work at Roseland Cottage and for the construction of the barn; and design and floor plans for the addition to the barn. The correspondence contains letters received by Henry Chandler Bowen relating to the construction work on Roseland Cottage. Several of the letters are from contractor, Samuel Underwood, requesting to be released from his contract; and other letters are from contractor, Edwin Eaton, detailing the work progress on the construction of Roseland Cottage and his decision to hire a Mr. Taylor of Brooklyn, New York, to complete the masonry work and a Mr. Joy of Worcester, Massachusetts, as foreman. The financial records include bills and receipts; drafts of checks; and work account records regarding the payment of laborers and the purchase of supplies associated with the construction of Roseland Cottage; the records were kept by Henry Chandler Bowen, Lewis Chamberlin, and Edwin Eaton. A collection of papers referred to as "Reminiscences of Roseland Cottage," describing the interior furnishings and rooms at Roseland Cottage, as recalled by Anna Mellon; photographs of a collection of paintin gs at Roseland Cottage (includes several photographs of Benjamin Franklin); and newspaper clippings relating to Roseland Cottage and its inhabitants, comprise the section of other materials. The series is arranged alphabetically by section, and thereunder chronologically. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Other bills and receipts, November 1846 - September 1850; includes payment receipts re: Lewis Chamberlin and Edwin Eaton, contractor, 1846-1850; MS006.02.03.04; Bowen family papers (MS006) Series II, Papers relating to the construction of Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1845-1969, undated (bulk: 1845-1851) (#6.25-6.27, 8.1-8.17, OB.1.4-OB.1.5), contains agreements and contracts (includes drafts); bills and receipts; building and construction specifications; correspondence; design and floor plans; drafts of checks; work account records; photographs; clippings; and a collection of papers describing the rooms at Roseland Cottage. The series is divided into three sections: contracts and specifications, financial records, and other materials. Contracts and specifications includes two drafts and a signed agreement between Henry Chandler Bowen and contractor, Samuel Underwood, regarding the furnishing of materials for construction of Roseland Cottage and an adjoining barn; specifications of architect, John C. Wells, for the carpentry and masonry work at Roseland Cottage and for the construction of the barn; and design and floor plans for the addition to the barn. The correspondence contains letters received by Henry Chandler Bowen relating to the construction work on Roseland Cottage. Several of the letters are from contractor, Samuel Underwood, requesting to be released from his contract; and other letters are from contractor, Edwin Eaton, detailing the work progress on the construction of Roseland Cottage and his decision to hire a Mr. Taylor of Brooklyn, New York, to complete the masonry work and a Mr. Joy of Worcester, Massachusetts, as foreman. The financial records include bills and receipts; drafts of checks; and work account records regarding the payment of laborers and the purchase of supplies associated with the construction of Roseland Cottage; the records were kept by Henry Chandler Bowen, Lewis Chamberlin, and Edwin Eaton. A collection of papers referred to as "Reminiscences of Roseland Cottage," describing the interior furnishings and rooms at Roseland Cottage, as recalled by Anna Mellon; photographs of a collection of paintin gs at Roseland Cottage (includes several photographs of Benjamin Franklin); and newspaper clippings relating to Roseland Cottage and its inhabitants, comprise the section of other materials. The series is arranged alphabetically by section, and thereunder chronologically. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Contracts and specifications, 1845, undated; MS006.02.08; Business records (1 file box, 1 oversize folder)
    - Agreement between Henry Chandler Bowen (1813-1896) and Samuel Underwood re: construction of a house and barn, October 13; includes typewritten copy and draft [2 copies], 1845; MS006.02.08.01; NOTE: See #6.26 for items removed [specifications] (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Specifications of Joseph Collins Wells (1814-1860), re: carpentry [2 copies] and masonry work on the house, 1845; MS006.02.08.02; NOTE: Items removed from #6.25. (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Specifications of Joseph Collins Wells (1814-1860), re: construction of the barn, 1845; MS006.02.08.03 (Box 6, folder 27)
    - Site plans for addition to the barn [photocopies], undated; MS006.02.08.04 (Box OB.3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: letters received by Henry Chandler Bowen (1813-1896) re: construction progress on the house, November-May, 1845-1848; MS006.02.09; NOTE: Contains oversize material. (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Financial records of Henry Chandler Bowen, 1845-1851; MS006.02.10; Financial records (1 file box)
    - Work accounts re: laborers, September-November; includes Lewis Chamberlin's work account, MS006.02.10.01 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Bills and receipts re: supplies, October-November, 1846; MS006.02.10.02 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Bills and receipts re: architect, Joseph Collins Wells (1814-1860), November 20 and July 12, 1846-1850; MS006.02.10.03 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Other bills and receipts, November-September; includes payment receipts re: Lewis Chamberlin and Edwin Eaton, 1846-1850; MS006.02.10.04 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Financial records of Lewis Chamberlin, 1845-1846; MS006.02.11; Financial records (1 file box)
    - Other bills and receipts re: supply purchases and laborer payments, September-November, 1845; MS006.02.11.01 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Work accounts re: payment of laborers, May 30, 1846; MS006.02.11.02 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Financial papers of Edwin Eaton, 1846-1847; MS006.02.12; Financial records (1 file box)
    - Bills and receipts re: shipping, February-November, 1846; MS006.02.12.01 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Drafts of checks to laborers, February-December, 1846; MS006.02.12.02 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Bills and receipts re: supply purchases for hardware, nails, screws, and lumber, April-July, 1846; MS006.02.12.03 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Work accounts re: payment of laborers, April-May, 1846-1847; MS006.02.12.04 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Other bills and receipts, June-September, 1846; MS006.02.12.05 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Work accounts re: bills submitted by laborers, September, 1846; MS006.02.12.06 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Work accounts re: payment of board by laborers, September-December, 1846; MS006.02.12.07 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Financial records, other: other bills and receipts re: construction of house, 1847; MS006.02.13 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Other materials, 1938-1969, undated; MS006.02.14; Family papers (1 file box)
    - Clippings re: life at Roseland Cottage, 1938-1969; MS006.02.14.01 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - "Reminiscences of Roseland Cottage," memories of Roseland Cottage as recalled by Anna Mellon, undated; MS006.02.14.02 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Photographs of the paintings at Roseland Cottage, undated; MS006.02.14.03 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Photographic material of the Bowen family of Woodstock, Connecticut, 1860-1965, undated, predominant 1860-1935; MS006.03; Photographic materials (5 file boxes, 1 folio box, 1 multi-purpose box, 1 oversize folder); Series III, Photographic material of the Bowen family of Woodstock, Connecticut, 1860-1965, undated (bulk, 1860-1935) (#8.18-12.14, FB.2.1, MB.1.1-MB.1.2, OB.3.9), contains portraits and group photographs; black and white photographs; color photographs; cabinet photographs; carte de visite; a mounted photograph; a hand-tinted and retouched photograph; a wood cut-out; tintypes; three photograph albums; and related letters. The series is arranged in four subseries. (HGO-02-105-A-E-302; HGO-02-105-A-E-101; HGO-02-105-A-E-106)
  - Photographs: portraits, 1862-1935, undated; MS006.03.01; Photographs (3 file boxes, 1 oversize folder); Subseries A, Photographs: portraits, 1862-1935, undated (#8.18-10.12, OB.3.9), contains black and white photographs and color photographs of individual members of the Bowen family and friends of the family; a mounted photograph (#8.29) and hand-tinted, retouched photograph (#8.25) of Henry Chandler Bowen (1813-1896); and a wood cut-out (possibly of George Chandler Holt, 1843-1931) (#8.30) of an unidentified Bowen family member. Also included in the subseries is an 1897 photograph of Herbert Wolcott Bowen (1856-1927) after his appointment as U.S. Consulate-General in Barcelona, Spain (#8.27); an undated photograph of Grace Aspinwall (Bowen) Hardy (1850-1940) with her doll, Lena Rivers, which is held by Historic New England (#9.7); an undated photograph of orator Henry Ward Beecher (1813-1887) (#8.19); a 1935 signed photograph of a Wilfred Grenfell (#9.5); an signed photograph of an Edward Thayer Monroe (#10.3); and an photograph of the Bowen family nurse, Jane S. Stuart (d. 1916) (#10.8). Additionally, the subseries contains a 1949 photograph taken by the U.S. Navy of Hamilton Holt (1872-1951), Governor Fuller Warren (1905-1973), and President Harry S Truman (U.S. President, 1945-1953), while attending an educators meeting in Florida on March 8 and an undated clipping with a photograph of Hamilton Holt (1872-1951), President Franklin Delano Roosevelt (U.S. President, 1933-1945), and First Lady (Anna) Eleanor Roosevelt (1884-1962) at Rollins College in Winter Park, Florida, (#9.11). The subseries is arranged alphabetically by surname; when applicable, women are identified by married name. (HGO-02-105-A-E-302; HGO-02-105-A-E-106)
    - Barney, Susan E. (Tappan) (dates unknown) [4 photographs], 1887, undated; MS006.03.01.01 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Beecher, Henry Ward (1813-1887) [1 photograph], undated; MS006.03.01.02 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Bowen, Clarence Winthrop (1852-1935) [5 photographs], 1901, undated; MS006.03.01.03; NOTE: See also #11.10 for related material (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Bowen, Edward Augustus (1847-1926) [3 photographs], 1871-1872, undated; MS006.03.01.04 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Bowen, Ellen (Holt) (1834-1903) [4 photographs], 1884, undated; MS006.03.01.05 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Bowen, Francis (dates unknown) [1 photograph], undated; MS006.03.01.06 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Bowen, Franklin Davis (1860-1940) [1 photograph], undated; MS006.03.01.07 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Bowen, George (1789-1846) [2 photographs], undated; MS006.03.01.08 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Bowen, Henry Chandler (1813-1896) [5 photograph], 1891-1893, undated; MS006.03.01.09; NOTE: Henry Chandler Bowen, hand-tinted and retouched photograph removed from #8.30 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Bowen, Henry Chandler (1813-1896), mounted photograph [1photograph], undated; MS006.03.01.10; NOTE: See #8.25 for item removed [hand-tinted and retouched photograph] (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Bowen, Henry Elliot (1845-1919) [1 photograph], undated; MS006.03.01.11 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Bowen, Herbert Wolcott (1856-1927), U.S. Consulate-General, Barcelona, Spain, October 15 [1 photograph], 1897; MS006.03.01.12 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Bowen, John Eliot (1858-1890) [3 photographs], 1890, undated; MS006.03.01.13 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Bowen, Lucy Maria (Tappan) (1825-1863) [4 photographs], undated; MS006.03.01.14 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Bowen, Lydia Wolcott (Eaton) (1793-1864) [1 photograph], 1862; MS006.03.01.15 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Bowen, Paul Holt (1868-1895) [2 photographs], undated; MS006.03.01.16 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Bowen, Roxana Atwater (Wentworth) (1854-1935) [2 photographs], undated; MS006.03.01.17 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Grenfell, Wilfred (dates unknown); includes signature [1 photograph], 1935; MS006.03.01.18 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Hardy, Arthur Sherburne (1847-1930) [3 photographs], undated; MS006.03.01.19 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Hardy, Grace Aspinwall (Bowen) (1850-1940): holding doll, Lena Rivers [2 photographs], undated; MS006.03.01.20; NOTE: See SPNEA textiles and household objects collection #2000.440, Museum Collection, for Grace Aspenwall's doll, Lena Rivers (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Holt, Constance (1879-1968) [1 of 2] [6 photographs], 1883-1905, undated; MS006.03.01.21 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Holt, Constance (1879-1968) [2 of 2] [3 photographs], 1883-1905, undated; MS006.03.01.22; NOTE: Group photograph with Constance Holt, undated, removed from #11.1 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Holt, George Chandler (1843-1931) [5 photographs], 1895, undated; MS006.03.01.23 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - [Possibly Holt, George Chandler (1843-1931)], wood cut-out, undated; MS006.03.01.23a; NOTE: Item removed from #10.12 (Box OB.3, Folder 9)
    - Holt, Hamilton (1872-1951); includes 1949 U.S. Navy photograph and undated clipping [3 photographs], 1949, undated; MS006.03.01.24 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Holt, Henry Chandler (1881-1955) [10 photographs], 1885-1897, undated; MS006.03.01.25 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Holt, Mary Louisa (Bowen) (1848-1925) [1 of 2] [9 photographs], 1867-1887, undated; MS006.03.01.26 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Holt, Mary Louisa (Bowen) (1848-1925) [2 of 2] [4 photographs], 1867-1887, undated; MS006.03.01.27 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Holt, Stuart (1876-1900) [1 of 2] [6 photographs], 1877-1898, undated; MS006.03.01.28 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Holt, Stuart (1876-1900) [2 of 2] [7 photographs], 1877-1898, undated; MS006.03.01.29 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Holt, Sylvia (1889-1945) [1 of 2] [8 photograph], 1893-1901, undated; MS006.03.01.31 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Holt, Sylvia (1889-1945) [2 of 2] [6 photograph], 1893-1901, undated; MS006.03.01.32 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Monroe, Edward Thayer (dates unknown); includes signature [1 photograph], undated; MS006.03.01.33 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Reed, Grace (Holt) (1874-1937) [3 photographs], 1888-1921; MS006.03.01.34; NOTE: Photograph of Grace (Holt) Reed, ca.1903, removed from #11.1 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Richardson, Alice Linden (Bowen) (1854-1948) [2 photograph], undated; MS006.03.01.35 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Richardson, Gardner (1884-1972) [5 photographs], 1888-1899, undated; MS006.03.01.36 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Richardson, Rufus Byam (1845-1914) [1 photograph], 1904; MS006.03.01.37 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Stuart, Jane S. (d. 1916), nurse [1 photograph], undated; MS006.03.01.38; NOTE: Item removed from #10.12 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Tappan, Arthur (1786-1865) [1 photograph], undated; MS006.03.01.39 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Tappan, Charles (dates unknown) [1 photograph], 1874; MS006.03.01.40 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Tappan, Lewis (1788-1873) [2 photographs], 1838, undated; MS006.03.01.41 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified [2 photographs], 1866, undated; MS006.03.01.42; NOTE: See #10.8 and OB.3.9 for items removed (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Photographs: groups, 1866-1965, undated, predominant 1886-1898; MS006.03.02; Photographs (2 file boxes); Subseries B, Photographs: groups, 1866-1965, undated (bulk, 1886-1898) (#10.13-10.31, 11.1-11.14), contains black and white photographs, color photographs, and related letters. The subseries includes group photographs of the Bowen family with such acquaintances as orator Henry Ward Beecher (1813-1887) (#10.13); author Harriet Beecher Stowe (1811-1896) (#10.13); and family nurse, Henrietta (#10.28). Also included in the subseries are photographs of Roseland Park and Roseland Cottage in Woodstock, Connecticut; events at the Bowen family house located at 90 Willow Street in Brooklyn, New York; two undated hunting party photographs taken by Nellie Chandler (dates unknown) at Roseland Park in Woodstock, Connecticut (#11.6); Herbert Wolcott Bowen's (1856-1927) house in Woodstock, Connecticut (#11.14); and the Aspinwall houses in Brookline, Massachusetts (#11.11). Additionally, the subseries contains photographs of several Fourth of July celebrations held at Roseland Cottage, which include group photographs with President Benjamin Harrison (U.S. President, 1889-1893) (#11.1-11.2); President William McKinley (U.S. President, 1897-1901) (#11.3, 11.9); and Julia Ward Howe (1819-1910) (#10.31), author of the "Battle Hymn of the Republic." An 1886 photograph of Clarence Winthrop Bowen (1852-1935) delivering an Independence Day address in Roseland Park (#11.10), and photographs of the U.S. flag flown out front of Roseland Cottage during the Independence Day celebrations (#11.14) are also included in the Fourth of July celebration photographs. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by surname, followed by general Bowen family photographs, and then by other photographs; when applicable, women are identified by married name. (HGO-02-105-A-E-302)
    - Beecher, Henry Ward and Harriet Beecher Stowe [1 photograph], undated; MS006.03.02.01 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Bowen, Clarence Winthrop; Fanny Chandler; Alice Linden (Bowen) Richardson; and others; includes letter from Fanny Chandler [1 photograph], 1866-1937; MS006.03.02.02 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Bowen, Clarence Winthrop; and Alice Linden (Bowen) Richardson [1 photograph], undated; MS006.03.02.03 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Bowen, Clarence Winthrop; Edward Augustus Bowen; Grace Aspinwall (Bowen) Hardy; and Evelyn Stoddard [1 photograph], undated; MS006.03.02.04; NOTE: See also #FB.2.1 for related material (Box 10, folder 16)
    - Bowen, Ellen (Holt) and Paul Holt Bowen [1 photograph], 1888; MS006.03.02.05 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Bowen, Franklin Davis; Herbert Wolcott Bowen; and John Eliot Bowen [1 photograph], 1866; MS006.03.02.06 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Bowen, Henry Chandler; Lucy Maria (Tappan) Bowen; and Henry Elliot Bowen [1 photograph], undated; MS006.03.02.07 (Box 10, Folder 19)